Guide to the William Dunlap Sargent Falconry papers, 1927-1965
Sargent, William Dunlap Falconry papers, 1927-1965
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
William Dunlap Sargent Falconry papers, 1927-1965
21-18-1314
William Dunlap Sargent, 1908-1965.
1.7 cubic ft.
Correspondence, photographs, drawings, and diagrams.
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Includes correspondence concerning falconry, including letters to a young falconer (1947-1948) containing much information on the sport; photographs of hawks and falcons Sargent trained as hunters; drawings of hawks and falcons; and diagrams of furniture and fittings used in falconry.
BIOGRAPHICAL NOTE
William Dunlap Sargent, was among the foremost authorities on falconry in America. Sargent studied ornithology at Cornell University under Arthur A. Allen, graduating in 1931, receiving an M.S. in 1933 and a Ph.D. in 1936. He taught limnology and ecology at Cornell, 1932-1936, and taught limnology, stream improvement, conservation, and ornithology at City College of New York. A noted bird artist, as well as scientist, he illustrated a number of books on biology.
CHRONOLOGY
1908 Born in Brooklyn, N.Y., May 15
1926 Graduated from the Lincoln School of Teacher's College Summer Staff Entomologist in the museum maintained by AMAH at Kanokwakke Lakes Scout Camp Entered Cornell University
1927 Summer Junior Nature Counselor, Camp Lincoln, Keeseville, N.Y.
1928 Entomology Museum at Kanokwakke Lakes Camp
1929 Summer Biological Survey of a trout stream for Tuscarora Club, Arena, N.Y.
1930 Summer member of West Virginia University Zoological Field Expedition under Dr. J.G. Needham
1931 B.S., Cornell
1930-1931 Biological Survey of Mashpee River for Mr. J.W. Farley, Boston, Mass.
1932 M.S., Cornell Summer Survey of North Hudson drainage, fish food unit
1932-1936 Instructor of Ecology and Limnology at Cornell
1936 Ph.D., Cornell, in Limnology
1937-1948 Biology Instructor at City College of N.Y.
1948-1961 Assistant Professor, C.C.N.Y.
1961-1965 Associate Professor, C.C.N.Y.
1965 Died
COLLECTION DESCRIPTION
Correspondence from the 1930s and 1940s concerning falconry, including letters to a young falconer (1947-1948) with much information on the sport; research and manuscripts on falcons, hawks and other birds containing locations of eyries, articles, notes and illustrations; photographs of hawks and falcons Sargent trained as hunters; drawings of hawks and falcons; and diagrams of furniture and fittings used in falconry.
SUBJECTS
Names:
Sargent, William Dunlap, 1908-1965.; Cornell University--Faculty.
Subjects:
Falconry.; Falcons.; Hawks.; Ornithology.; College teachers.; Falconers.; Ornithologists.; Ornithological illustration.; Birds--Pictorial works.
Form and Genre Terms:
Drawings.; Photographs.
INFORMATION FOR USERS
RELATED MATERIAL
Correspondence from Sargent can be found in the Arthur Augustus Allen papers, #21-18-1255 with whom he worked at the Laboratory of Ornithology.
SERIES LIST
Series I. Correspondence on Falconry
Box 1
Series II. Student Materials
Box 1
Series III. Research and Manuscripts on Falcons, Hawks and other Birds
Boxes 1 & 6-8
Articles and Speeches by Sargent
Research: Subject Files
Research: Card Files
Series IV. Photographic Materials
Box 5
CONTAINER LIST
- Series I. Correspondence on Falconry
  - Correspondence, 1927-1941; Dr. Walter R. Spofford, Minard Stevens, Louis J. Halle, Jr. (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence, 1941-1945; Thomas Ennenga, Louis Halle, Jr., William Russell, Jr., Walter Spofford, Robert Stabler (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence, 1947-1948; Bob Maull, Jr. (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence, 1946-1950; Richard Pough, Howard Richardson, William Russell, Jr., Williston Shor, Walter Spofford (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence, 1952, 1953, 1963, 1965, and n.d.; Edward Reid, Walter Spofford, Minard Stevens, includes response to card dated 11-6-33 from Eugene Smith that is in box 1 folder 1 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Series II. Student Materials
  - Ornithology lecture notes, 1929-1934; Lectures on definition, characteristics, origin and migration of birds, and falconry (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Thesis: "The Training of a Red-Tailed Hawk" (2 copies), 1936 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Series III. Research and Manuscripts on Falcons, Hawks and Other Birds
  - Articles and Speeches by Sargent
    - Draft speeches and published and unpublished articles, 1934-1939 & n.d.; "A Visit with the Falconer of the Falcon Field," "Hawks," "Nest Parasitism of Hawks," "The Prairie Falcons of Williams Canyon Colorado," "The Flying Dutchess," "The Training of a Red-Tailed Hawk," "The Internal Thoracic Skeleton of the Dragonflies" (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Research: Subject Files
    - Anatomy and osteology (drawings, reprints), 1927, 1941, & n.d.; William L. Engels, E. Sunderville (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Bibliographical notes, undated (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Bird-banding (bulletin), undated; "How to Band Nestling Hawks, Owls, and Eagles" (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Care and management (articles, thesis), 1826, 1890, 1935, 1936; John Downes, "Observations on Falconry"; Col. E. Delme Radcliff, "Falconry"; George G. Goodwin, "Winged Monarchs of the Air" (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Drawings, sketches, and watercolors of falcons, undated (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Falcon eyries (lists, magazine photographs), undated; Locations of nests of falcons, in the U.S. and abroad (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Falcon eyries (lists, magazine photographs), undated; Locations of falcon nests by state: Alabama, Alaska, Arizona, California, Colorado, Connecticut, Idaho, Illinois, Indiana, Iowa, Kansas, Kentucky, Maine (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Falcon eyries (lists, magazine photographs), undated; Locations of falcon nests by state: Maryland, Massachusetts, Michigan, Minnesota, Montana, Nebraska, New Hampshire (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - Falcon eyries (lists, magazine photographs), undated; Locations of falcon nests by state: New Jersey, New Mexico, New York, North Carolina, North Dakota, Ohio, Oregon (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - Falcon eyries (lists, magazine photographs), 1940, 1950 & undated; Locations of falcon nests by state: Pennsylvania (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - Falcon eyries (lists, magazine photographs), undated; Locations of falcon nests by state or territory: South Carolina, South Dakota, Tennessee, Texas, Utah, Vermont, Virginia, Washington, West Virginia, Wisconsin, Wyoming, Panama Canal Zone and Puerto Rico (Box 1, Folder 19)
    - Falcon measurements and weights, undated; Weight and measurements of several falcon species, including the peregrine, sparrow hawk, and pigeon hawk (Box 1, Folder 20)
    - Falcon notes, undated; Vitamins, minerals, mews, medicine, hooding, scouring, imping, flying falcons, falcon sounds, caring for hawks, peregrine watching (Box 1, Folder 21)
    - Falcon records, undated; Statistics and activities of three peregrines and one prairie falcon (Box 1, Folder 22)
    - Falcons, Keys and Taxonomy of (manuscripts), undated; Descriptions and characteristics of the families of falcons, article on taxonomy of the Palaearctic Goshawk (Box 1, Folder 23)
    - Furniture and fittings (articles, photos, mss. diagrams), undated; Trappings and gear used in falconry with diagrams (Box 1, Folder 24)
    - Falconry clippings, 1930-1948 & n.d.; Art of falconry, early falconry, Sargent's work (Box 1, Folder 25)
    - List of Falcon specimens, undated; Lists of collected American Falconiformes (Box 1, Folder 26)
    - Falconry, bulletins and journals, 1940-1943 & 1954; List of falconers, Journals of American Falconers' Association, Journals of the Falconers' Association of North America, Bulletins of Westchester Hawking Club and American Amateur Falconers' Association (Box 1, Folder 27)
    - Falconry articles, 1913-1939; Hawk and falcon articles, 1920 National Geographic article by Louis A. Fuertes (Box 1, Folder 28)
    - Falconry articles, 1940-1948; Articles on eagles, hawks, falcons (Box 1, Folder 29)
    - Falconry articles, 1952-1964 & n.d.; Articles on eagles, falcons, albatross (Box 1, Folder 30)
    - Falcons and hawks (bulletins, reprints, reports, advertising material, 2 photos), 1929-1943 & n.d.; U.S. Dept. Agr. bulletins on parasites and diseases in poultry, mites and lice on poultry, movie ad with two photos, hawk reprints (Box 1, Folder 31)
    - Falcon, Hawk, Vulture and Eagle pictures, undated; Magazine clippings, lithographs (Box 1, Folder 32)
    - Field identification of Hawks, 1939; Illustrations of characteristics of hawks for field identification, including wingspread dimensions (Box 1, Folder 33)
    - Hawk migration, 1939-1940; Annual report of Hawk Mountain Sanctuary Association, Goshawk flight (Box 1, Folder 34)
    - Hawks: Notes on living birds, 1938-1940; Study skin notes on collected hawks (Box 1, Folder 35)
    - Hawks, owls, and other birds of prey, 1929-1939; Articles on hawks and owls; birds of prey; food habits of Buteo hawks, eagles, hawks, and vultures; the bald eagle (Box 1, Folder 36)
    - Hawks--trapping, 1935 & n.d.; Articles on shooting hawks, methods of hawk trapping (Box 1, Folder 37)
    - Maps, nest sites marked, undated; California, Colorado, Connecticut, Maryland, Massachusetts, Nevada, New Hampshire, New Jersey, New Mexico (Box 1, Folder 38)
    - Maps, nest sites marked, undated; New York, Pennsylvania, Rhode Island, Tennessee, Virginia (Box 1, Folder 39)
    - Maps, 1916 and n.d.; North America, Canada, Newfoundland and Greenland, United States with nesting sites of the duck hawk (peregrine falcon) (Box 1, Folder 40)
    - "Observations on the Peregrine Falcon" by Desmond Nethersole-Thompson (typescript--published article), undated (Box 1, Folder 41)
    - Parasitology and pathology (notes, articles, photos), 1925 and n.d., undated; Notes on two diseases of hawks, articles on blood parasites of birds, and external parasites of birds; list of the cestodes (worms) of the falcons; note on delousing hawks (Box 1, Folder 42)
    - Quarry (magazine articles and pictures), 1940, undated; Prey of the falcons (Box 1, Folder 43)
    - Quotations, undated; Falconry quotations from Shakespeare, poems, a German quotation, and the Falconer's Song (Box 1, Folder 44)
    - Study skin notes, undated; Peregrine falcon study skin statistics (Box 1, Folder 45)
    - Wings (diagrams, notes, magazine illustrations), undated; Wings of the falcon with drawings showing various movements and positions (Box 1, Folder 46)
    - Falcon drawing, undated (Box 8, Folder 1)
    - "Falconry," Field, Aug. 5, 1871 (photocopy), undated (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - Research: Card Files
    - Card file (3"x5") on falconry, Books, articles and manuscripts by title and author, falconry topic references, locations of eyries by country and state (Box 6)
    - Card file (3"x5"), References on birds and falcons, address index, bibliography on thorax of odonata (Box 7)
- Series IV. Photographs
  - Photographic prints of falcons and climbing expeditions to eyries, 1920s-1940s & n.d. (Box 5)